<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

 <tt xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1"  xmlns:tts="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1#styling">
  <head>
   <styling>
    <style id="1" tts:textAlign="center" tts:color="#555555" tts:backgroundColor="#DFDFDF" tts:fontSize="16" tts:fontFamily="Verdana" tts:wrapOption="wrap"/>
   </styling>
  </head>
  <body>
   <div xml:lang="en" style="1">
    <p begin="00:00:00.63" dur="00:00:07.55">So, the way a mother rat takes care<br/>of its pups is by licking and grooming,</p>
    <p begin="00:00:08.18" dur="00:00:02.90">nipple switching and arch back nursing.</p>
    <p begin="00:00:11.08" dur="00:00:05.74">So there are rats that do a lot of licking and<br/>grooming and there are rats that do very little</p>
    <p begin="00:00:16.82" dur="00:00:07.53">but most rats are in between, so that<br/>resembles human behavior as well, right,</p>
    <p begin="00:00:24.35" dur="00:00:03.66">you have mothers that are highly<br/>mothering and mothers that could care less</p>
    <p begin="00:00:28.01" dur="00:00:02.02">and most mothers are somewhere in between.</p>
    <p begin="00:00:30.03" dur="00:00:04.28">So if you look at these rats, so all you do you<br/>observe them and you put them in separate cages</p>
    <p begin="00:00:34.31" dur="00:00:04.36">so you put the high lickers in one cage, not the<br/>mothers but the offspring, and the low lickers</p>
    <p begin="00:00:38.67" dur="00:00:05.08">in another cage and then you let them grow and<br/>they&apos;re adults now, the mothers are long buried</p>
    <p begin="00:00:43.75" dur="00:00:05.78">and you look in the brain and you see that<br/>those who had high licking mothers express a lot</p>
    <p begin="00:00:49.53" dur="00:00:06.95">of glucocorticoid receptor gene and those<br/>who are low lickers express very little,</p>
    <p begin="00:00:56.48" dur="00:00:05.71">that reflects a number of receptors and<br/>that results in a different stress response.</p>
    <p begin="00:01:02.19" dur="00:00:05.15">But this is not the only difference<br/>we found. There were hundreds</p>
    <p begin="00:01:07.34" dur="00:00:03.70">of genes that are differently expressed.</p>
    <p begin="00:01:11.04" dur="00:00:02.65">So if you get a mutation, polymorphism once</p>
    <p begin="00:01:13.69" dur="00:00:05.39">in a million. Here just the motherly love<br/>changes hundreds of genes in one shot</p>
    <p begin="00:01:19.08" dur="00:00:05.72">and it changes them in a very stable<br/>way. That you can look at the old rat</p>
    <p begin="00:01:24.80" dur="00:00:02.11">and you can say whether it was licked or not.</p>
    <p begin="00:01:26.91" dur="00:00:03.82">But you can also say by behavior<br/>so if you walk to the cages --</p>
    <p begin="00:01:30.73" dur="00:00:08.19">to the room, the rats that were poorly licked<br/>are highly anxious, hard to handle, aggressive</p>
    <p begin="00:01:38.92" dur="00:00:04.07">and the rats that were very well handled</p>
    <p begin="00:01:42.99" dur="00:00:04.92">as little pups they&apos;re much more<br/>relaxed, much easier to handle.</p>
    <p begin="00:01:47.91" dur="00:00:06.12">So, you know, like every technician in<br/>the lab knows, looking at the adult rat,</p>
    <p begin="00:01:54.03" dur="00:00:03.38">how it was licked when it was a little pup.</p>
    <p begin="00:01:57.41" dur="00:00:06.07">And the question, of course, is<br/>mechanism, how does this work?</p>
   </div>
  </body>
</tt>
